Guide to the Women in the West: Microfilm Sets
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Women in the West: Microfilm Sets
1753-1919
WA MFM 1-6
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
(6 microfilms)
Six microfilm sets: Frontier Women, Frontier Women II, Frontier Women III, Women in California, Women in California II, and Mormon Women.
Other Storage Formats: Microfilm [6 reels]
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Original materials catalogued separately. For provenance information, consult the catalog record for each title.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
In 1979 an effort was made to microfilm women-related collections and items in the Western Americana collection. Six microfilm sets were created: Frontier Women, Frontier Women II, Frontier Women III, Women in California, Women in California II, and Mormon Women. A finding aid was created for the film and was included on each reel.
At the time that the materials were filmed, some items were cataloged but many others were not. Since that time, most of the material has been cataloged. A new guide was needed to reflect the cataloged status of the items on the film.
The following list is meant to serve as a guide to placement of items on the microfilm reels. The catalog number, main entry, title, and date information is given for each item or collection. For the full bibliographical descriptions of materials cited in this list, the researcher should consult the main catalog record.
Several of the items filmed are part of larger collections, some of which have not been filmed in their entirety. In such cases, a note gives the name of the collection in which the item[s] will be found and the catalog number of the larger collection.
- Frontier women microfilm set, 1849-1913; WA MFM 1; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Women's diaries, correspondence, and related papers. Written by women who were early settlers in California, Colorado, Idaho, Oregon, and Washington. Includes accounts of the westward journey and of life on the frontier.
  - Mary Burrell's book, 1854
    Existence and Location of Originals
    Request this item, WA MSS 58, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary Rockwood Powers. The overland route, leaves from the journal of a California emigrant, 1859
    Request this item, WA MSS 387, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Celinda E. Hines. Overland journey from Hastings, Oswego County, New York, to Portland, Oregon, 1853
    Request this item, WA MSS 424, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sarah Green Davis. Diary of an overland journey to California, 1849-50
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1320, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Martha Missouri Bishop Moore. Journal of a trip to California, 1860
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1438, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Louisa Cook Walters papers, 1852-91
    Incl: R.M. Fuller, Letters to Louisa Cook
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1656, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Lucy H. Fosdick. Across the plains in 61
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1410 F786, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Jennie T. Kimball. Diary of a trip to California, 1876-77
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1683, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Lillie I. Wells. My journey to California, n.d.
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1669 W4621, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Maria R. Hodgdon. Journal of a voyage from Boston to San Francisco in the ship Golden Rocket commanded by Capt. Charles Pendleton, 1859-60
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1425, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Julia R. Collins. Letters, 1878-82
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1268, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Almira Markell papers, 1881-1913
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1660, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
- Frontier women II microfilm set, 1821-1919; WA MFM 2
  Women's letters and manuscripts. Written by early settlers of Alaska, Iowa, Kansas, Minnesota, Missouri, Oklahoma, Oregon, Utah, and Washington.
  - Miscellaneous Missouri letters, 1853-1902
    Note: partially filmed, see box listing for list of letters filmed
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1661, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Caroline M. Moss. Letter to Captain O. P. Moss, 1846 Nov 2
    Request this item, WA MSS S-563 M855, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - George H. Hall. Overland letters, 1849-50
    Request this item, WA MSS S-288 H1422, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Noah Pease. Letters, 1841-55
    Incl: Letters from Cyrus Russell, Flavia Pease, and Martin F. Pease
    Request this item, WA MSS S-21 P321, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sallie and J. Bowers. Letters, 1870-71
    In: Harrison Lawrence Family Correspondence (WA MSS S-1670 L436)
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1670 L436, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sue Hill. Letters, 1868-69
    Request the original materials from the Malick Family Papers (WA MSS-1298).
  - Mary Ann Scott. Letter: Worthington, Ohio, to Mrs. Emily Piatt, Hartford, Indiana
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1650 Sco85, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - William Shively. Letter: Zwingle, Iowa, to Joseph Lenhart, 1865 Jul 9
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1651 Sh69, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Tabitha Lowe Stennett. Untitled account of growing up in Iowa, 1905 Jan 10
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1653 St42, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - John Brown family letters: Kansas, 1855-56
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1671 B8131, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Lettie E. Garrison. Letter: to my dear sister, 1862 Sep 27
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1199 G193, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary Rice. Letter: to her sister, Hannah Rice, 1835[?] Nov 15
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1096 R365, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Harriet Woolley. Letterbook, 1821-34
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1682, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary C. Denver. Letter: to J. W. Denver, 1847 Oct 6
    Request this item, WA MSS S-528 D439, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Louise C. Denver. Mexican War Pension, n.d.
    Request this item, WA MSS S-587 D4375, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Abigail Raymond Smith. Missionary letters, 1836-56
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1284 Sm5, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Eliza Hart Spalding. Note, 1843 Aug 8
    Request this item, WA MSS 434, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary Hayden. Letter: to Harry M. Boutelle, 1887 May 8
    Request this item, WA MSS S-280 H324, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sarah McAllister Hartman. Reminiscences, n.d.
    Request this item, WA MSS 247, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Frances Fuller Victor: Letters to Elwood Evans, 1865-86
    In: Elwood Evans Papers (WA MSS 172)
    Request this item, WA MSS 172, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Paulina Cohen. Letter: to R. E. Coontz, 1892 Mar 3
    Request this item, WA MSS S-359 C66, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mattie Pajoman. Letter: Afognak, Alaska, to Miss Saunders, 1912 Jul 5
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1649 P168, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Hukill Fickes. Diary, 1856-57
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1684 F446, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Anne Ellis. Letters, 1851-97
    In: William Ellis. Letters to his Wife Cornelia (WA MSS S-41)
    Request this item, WA MSS S-41, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Catherine Hutton. Account of a visit by George Catlin, 1844[?]
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1646 H979, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - George Sand. Letter: to Edouard Thomas Charton
    Request this item, WA MSS S-461 Sa56, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary Benjamin Kirkpatrick. Letters: to her husband Charlie, 1864-65
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1255 K636, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer. Letter: to Mr. Thomas A. Warburton, 1905 Mar 16
    Request this item, WA MSS 127, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer. Letters: to Mrs. Kingsley, 1886-89
    Request this item, WA MSS S-93 C966, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer. Letter: to Mr. Bagby, 1889 Feb 6
    Request this item, WA MSS S-393 C966, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer. Letter: to Miss Watson, n.d.
    In: George Armstrong Custer Papers (WA MSS S-1643)
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1643, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer. Letter: to [Frederick Samuel] Dellenbaugh, 1919 Mar 26
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1641 C966, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer. Letter: to General Wright, 1888 May 20
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1642 C966, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Jessie Benton Frémont. Letter: St. Louis, to Mr. Claiborne, 1843 Oct 30
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1668 F8861, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
- Frontier women III microfilm set, circa 1823-1894; WA MFM 3
  Women's letters, manuscripts, and other papers. Writers include early settlers of Arkansas, Kansas, Oregon, and Washington.
  - Blaine family letters, 1853-58
    Request this item, WA MSS 34, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sophronia Sumner Hitchcock. Dwight Mission map, [1823?]
    Map of the Dwight Mission, Pope County, Arkansas
    Request this item, WA MSS 257, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Valentine McGillycuddy. Army expedition notebook, 1876-77
    Request this item, WA MSS S-5, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Ella C. Granger: Letter to Col. Manning, 1879 Jul 25
    In: George A. Manning Letters (WA MSS 326)
    Request this item, WA MSS 326, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mrs. L. Sperry. Letter: to her son Anson Sperry, 1849 Sep 19
    Request this item, WA MSS 438, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Fort life on the frontier, 1868[?]
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1645 F7751, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Tintypes [of Lorenzo and Olive Oatman], 1857
    Request this item, WA MSS 362, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary Austin Holley. Letters, 1837 (Box 2)
    In: The Thomas W. Streeter Collection of Texas Manuscripts (WA MSS S-498)
  - Eliza Huston. Letter, 1852 Jun 21
  - Emily Austin Bryan Perry. Letter, 1838
  - Sarah Ann Wharton. Letters, 1836, n.d.
  - Caspar Wever Collins papers, 1862-65
    Request this item, WA MSS 98, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Frances Fuller Victor. Manuscript annotations and criticisms of William H. Gray's Did Dr. Whitman Save Oregon?, [1881]
    Bound in: Zc74 881gr
    Request this item, "WA MSS 496, bound in Zc74 881gr: Gray, W. H., Did Dr. Whitmen Save Oregon? (Astoria: 1881?), through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Eliza Clendenin. Travel diary, 1894 Jun-Oct
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1679, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Elizabeth Kerr. Correspondence with Mrs. Simcoe, 1838-45
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1647 K461, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Malick family papers, 1848-69
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1298, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
- Women in California microfilm set, 1849-1914; WA MFM 4
  Letters, diaries, and other manuscripts written by women who were early settlers in California.
  - A journal kept by Caroline Williams, 1858-62
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1680, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary E. Clark. Daily journal, 1859-60
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1267, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Ella Pearson. Diary, 1869-70
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1430 P317, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Abby T. Leighton Mansur. Correspondence, 1852-74
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1258 M318, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary S. D. Smith. Letters of a voyage to California in 1853-1854, n.d.
    Request this item, WA MSS S-798 Sm62, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary M. Allen. Letter to Mrs. Marianne P. Longfellow, 1850 Oct 20
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1207 A154, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Kate Lynch. Letter to her brother, 1864 Jun 5
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1252 L98, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Reminiscences of Mrs. E. A. Van Court, 1914 Mar 26
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1665 V279, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Dorcas Andrews. Letter: California, to Sarah W. Dell, 1852 Jan 9
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1640 An26, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Olive B. Bennett. Letter to her son Edward, 1861 Sep 3
    In: California Letters (WA MSS S-1337)
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1337, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mrs. Willard. Letter to her son, 1865 Jul 24
  - Lucetta Dennis Rogers. California letters, 1853-82
    Request this item, WA MSS S-731 R632, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Emily Slater. Letter to dear daughter Adeline, 1863 Jan 18
    Request this item, WA MSS S-785 S115, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Nancy M. Curry Lewis. Letter to her daughter Fannie, 1852 Jun 26
    Request this item, WA MSS S-730 L588, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Julia A. C. Bourne. Letter, 1856 Jun 2
    Request this item, WA MSS S-736 B667, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Helen Nye. Letters, 1852-71
    Request this item, WA MSS S-725 N9835, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Betsey Gordon. Letter to her father, 1854 Feb 28
    Request this item, WA MSS S-726 G653, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Jerusha Deming Merrill. Letters, 1849, 1853
    Request this item, WA MSS S-789 M552, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Jerusha Deming Merrill. California letters, 1849-51
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1114 M552, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary Bean Simonds Ballou. Voyage to California, 1851-52
    Request this item, WA MSS S-681, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Leffingwell family letters, 1853-76
    Request this item, WA MSS 299, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Martha Lawrence. Letter to her aunt and uncle, 1876 Apr 7
- Women in California II microfilm set, 1753-1875; WA MFM 5
  Letters, manuscripts, and other papers of women who were early settlers in California.
  - Anna Maria Sparks. Lease of land in San Francisco, 1851 May 12
    In: Joseph Libby Folman Papers (WA MSS S-238 F73)
    Request this item, WA MSS S-238 F73, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Marquesa de las Torres de Rada Peña Gertrudis. Estate description, 1753 Sep 5
    Request this item, WA MSS S-663 P37, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Francisco Tompez. Account of the will of the late Marquesa de las Torres de Rada Peña Gertrudis, n.d.
    Request this item, WA MSS S-2810 D6593, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Emma Whittier. Letters to Anna Patten, 1875 May-Dec
    Request this item, WA MSS S1657 W618, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sarah E. McLean. Diary, 1855-72
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1681, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Emma D. Hunt. Diary, 1883-84
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1129, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Rowena and Stephen Crary family papers, 1852-74
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1659, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
- Mormon women microfilm set, 1839-1881; WA MFM 6
  Letters and other papers of Mormon women.
  - Bringhurst family. Mormon letters, 1848-56
    Request this item, WA MSS 48, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Joseph Smith papers, 1839-46
    Request this item, WA MSS 430, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Sarah Jane Kent. Power of attorney, 1861 May 1
    Request this item, WA MSS S-408 K418, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Ann Eliza Young. Letter to S. L. Beidler, 1878 Nov 27
    Request this item, WA MSS S-385 Y839, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Ann Eliza Young. Letter to Mrs. Froiseth, 1881 Mar 19
    Request this item, WA MSS S-469 Y839, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Ann Eliza Young. Letter to Mrs. Froiseth, 1881 Apr 14
    Request this item, WA MSS S-470 Y839, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Mary E. Smith. Letter: American Fork, Utah, to Asabel Tyrell, 1874 Jan 30
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1652 Sm621, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.
  - Female Relief Society of Nauvoo. Manuscript fragment, 1843, n.d.
    Request this item, WA MSS S-1644 F349, through Orbis, the library's online catalog.